So I'm sitting here with Mike Lampras, who was the chairman of Silvergate, deeply involved
in that bank and very knowledgeable in terms of the situation.
This is very, I'm very excited to have Mike, first of all, so thank you for joining us.
Really appreciate it.
Thank you.
You know, you've got a great show.
It's great to be part of it.
And today's a very auspicious and exciting day, at least the day on which we're publishing
this episode.
The Senate is having a hearing on debanking and tomorrow the House is going to be having
a hearing on Operation Chokepoint 2.0.
So you know, it's all happening in Washington.
We're going to get to the bottom of this, but you know, I'm so glad you agreed to come
on.
It's time to tell the story from Silvergate's and from your perspective, and no one's done
it yet, you know, so couldn't be more excited to have you on this podcast than we talked
about a lot.
But there's no substitute from, you know, hearing it from you directly.
So so happy with us today.
That's great.
And there's lots of reasons people haven't been talking about it.
But I think the time is right to begin to talk about it.
So I think maybe before we start, why don't you just tell us about yourself?
You've had a very interesting career all across, you know, many different areas of
life, law, banking, tech, crypto as well.
So briefly recap for us how you came to be chairman of Silvergate.
Sure.
Well, I see myself as a lawyer at heart with a broader background than perhaps most lawyers
have.
But for me, it started, you know, I started essentially as almost a regulator.
I worked at got a White House fellowship after a little bit after law school and worked in
the Department of Justice.
Thoroughly enjoyed that experience and learned a ton from it, got a lot of respect for the
people who work in government.
Then went out and practiced law, became general counsel of a stock exchange, the old Pacifico
Stock Exchange, and went back into government to come and assist the United States attorney
and then rolled back out to become a lawyer at Silvergate Bank.
And as a Silvergate Bank, where I first discovered crypto, it was very early in the crypto experience.
Silvergate didn't even know it had crypto clients.
We ultimately found out that we had some and the question came up sort of, can we as a
bank, I'm sorry, Silicon Valley Bank, I hope I didn't say Silvergate, Silicon Valley Bank,
you know, can we as a bank, regulated financial institution, can we bank these guys?
So I looked into that issue that became my issue to deal with.
And as you often hear, I went down the rabbit hole and loved it.
Ultimately it turned out that the banks, Silicon Valley Bank, you know, made a risk based decision
that it wasn't appropriate for them to get too deeply involved.
I made a risk based decision that it was very appropriate for me to get more involved.
And so I left to go join a company called Bitnet, which was an early Bitcoin payments
company.
We sold that to Rakuten and then I moved over to Coinbase where I became one of the
early lawyers on that team and helped guide Coinbase through its hyper growth period.
And that was a pretty big crash course in dealing with regulators from that side of
things and been doing that ever since essentially.
I was an executive in residence at A16Z Crypto and have been sitting on boards of DeFi Crypto
with some fintech companies, primarily offering expertise in the regulatory regimes that are
out there and the best way to respond to them.
It was at, I should have mentioned, I apologize, when I was at Bitnet early on, I crossed paths
with Silvergate Bank.
It had just begun to get into crypto, it was about 2014 or so.
And I think Bitnet was one of the first five customers Silvergate had.
So I began to know them as a customer.
And then as years went on, the team there asked me to join the board, which I did in
2019.
I'm not sure the exact date there and ultimately became chair before going through this most
recent experience with them.
Wow, what an incredible background.
You've seen it from both sides, you know, being inside of the DOJ and being involved
in Coinbase.
Obviously, Coinbase had interesting banking issues early in their history.
And Andreessen, I think, intervened, I think is the story.
And that's one of the reasons they were able to survive and thrive.
It's really incredible that banks were able to pick winners and losers in the space by
who they chose to bank and didn't bank.
And I'd love to say there's some great science to it, but I don't think there was.
I mean, I think it was much, much more haphazard than that.
Yeah, I mean, you know, we're going to talk about debanking.
And, you know, I started complaining about that loudly in early twenty three.
But bank access has been a huge problem in this industry for years.
And it's really a matter of if you had it, then you were able to survive.
And if you didn't, you know, that's it was just one of those unfortunate things about
the crypto space.
So Silvergate, when did Silvergate start to explicitly focus on supporting the crypto
sector? So around 2013 is when they did that.
But prior to that, Silvergate was a, you know, a small southern California commercial
real estate, primarily financial institution, a bank like like many others.
It never really grew at any significant size.
And then in 2013, they began to lean in on the crypto industry, identified that as a
legal industry that wasn't adequately banked.
And the demand was was very strong.
And so they leaned in and said, we want to do that.
We want to do it in the right way.
Now, the Silvergate exchange network, that was one of the things that I think turbo
charge Silvergate's growth.
Would that did that begin in 2017?
Do I have that right? 2016, I believe you got about right.
Yeah. And so for those that aren't familiar, this was an intrabank settlement
network. So if you were a client of Silvergate, you could use Sun to settle up in real
time 24 7, right?
That's exactly right. And this grew to be a very important piece of financial
infrastructure for the crypto industry.
Yeah, it did. And the reason for that is that Silvergate itself was was banking so
many customers that what the Silvergate exchange network enabled Silvergate
customers to do was settle 24 7 with other Silvergate customers.
And, you know, and that, as you know, it's quite clunky if you're trying to use ACH
transfers or wires or something to pay somebody.
And so it was much closer to instantaneous.
And it was a huge benefit to people in the crypto industry.
So in let's say we'll start the story in late twenty, twenty two, when the FGX
collapse occurred, how what portion of Silvergate's business was crypto in terms of
depository base?
It was not literally 100 percent, but it was very close.
You know, I would say 98 percent.
Yeah. And so even more than Signature as a share.
Oh, yes. Signature had a larger financial footprint outside of crypto.
Absolutely. So the FGX collapse occurs in November 2022.
Silvergate suffers outflows.
Will you just sort of recap for us what happened all the way through to March
2023? So sorry, it grew, as we mentioned, started, you know, in 2013, looking in
crypto took a long time for Silvergate to get a billion dollars in deposits.
Then fairly quickly, it began to grow.
And by November 2022, Silvergate was doing around 14 billion dollars in deposits.
So a lot of growth very successfully, I think, handled.
Then there was during the FTX fraud and debacle that followed it.
There was a run on Silvergate Bank, as there were in other institutions, by the way, at
that time. So sorry, it went from 14 billion down to about four billion in
deposits in, I want to say, two months.
And sorry, I was able to handle that, by the way.
We were able to give depositors all their money back.
Which is kind of that's sort of unheard of for a bank.
It's absolutely. There's a reason, by the way, that it was so it was able to do that.
And that's because Silvergate realized early on that we were in a volatile industry.
Right. And so we were not a traditional fractional reserve bank that would loan out, you
know, 90 percent of its deposits, all of Silvergate's deposits, essentially all of
Silvergate's deposit being held in U.S.
dollars or U.S. dollar equivalents like Treasury bills.
And that was that was because we knew there may be, you know, huge swings into
deposit base. And so Silvergate was, I think, uniquely positioned to survive something
like that. It did survive it, which is pretty incredible.
We we don't think that's November.
So we paid everything off and we'd be in January of twenty twenty three.
Silvergate was positioned to to begin to grow back.
Right. We were OK. We're ready. We could be found on the floor.
We're set. Let's go build.
And we all know in the crypto industry that there are ebbs and flows.
And so we thought this is, you know, quite an ebb.
But we can we can build ourselves back into the next cycle.
Whenever it comes, we'll be ready.
And then our our regulators stepped in and essentially made that impossible.
And we could talk about that.
But it was it was done in both.
There was a couple of public statements that were made by regulators.
Joint statements about banks concentrations in the crypto industry,
indicating that was a concern, a safety and soundness issue.
When we became aware of that, we.
Tried to figure out a way forward, like, what's the best way for us to deal with this?
There have been, I think, published reports that regulators were insisting
that banks not be concentrated more than about 15 percent of their business
with companies that do crypto business.
And to be clear, if I haven't done this, I haven't said this.
Silvergate was was dealing in US dollars.
Silvergate was not dealing in either Bitcoin or anything else.
It was dealing in US dollars.
There's one small exception, whether I think one or maybe two loans
that were secured or over secured by Bitcoin.
But other than that, everything they did was US dollars.
So as mentioned, their published reports saying they couldn't go more than 15
percent focused on or doing business with crypto companies.
If that were the case, of course, Silvergate couldn't continue its business model
because you're going from 98 percent to 15 percent overnight.
So what do you do?
Well, you can't just magically find the way percentages work.
You can't shrink yourself to 15 percent.
That's impossible if you're at nearly 100 percent. Right.
So you'd have to grow or sell yourself.
But, you know, there are probably some other options.
And the board had a lot of a lot of big decisions to make.
And we took this stuff very seriously.
Fiduciaries for for investors, representative customers, employees
and explored any other way we could think of to create a new business model
that would meet their regulatory needs.
Unfortunately, at the same time, you mentioned Signature earlier.
The backdrop to all this was Signature was was not permitted
to sell its crypto related deposits or its signet,
which is sort of the equivalent that Signature had.
And what that meant was we were at Silvergate.
It was very, very difficult, if not impossible, to sell
our crypto related deposits to any financial institution
because they they knew the regulators wouldn't accept it.
So ultimately, we decided to
to wind down the bank just to voluntarily liquidate the bank,
which we which we did.
And we thought that was the most prudent thing to do to protect everybody
and to get, you know, to find a path forward for
investors, you know, our shareholders, our customers and everyone.
Unfortunately, in that process,
the net result was that nearly 1700 customers were
were in effect debanked because Silvergate was shutting down.
And, you know, my personal opinion is that that was
that was the intent of the of the regulatory demands that were made.
So I want to get into these specific events in a minute.
But what has happened at Silvergate since then?
I mean, it's actually still it's being restructured.
Is the long and short of it. Right.
Yeah. So that there are a lot of things happen.
But the first thing, OK, we stopped accepting deposits pretty quickly
in March, made this decision in March, stopped accepting new deposits in March
by of 23. I'm sorry.
By November of 23, we had returned all the deposits.
So everybody got their money back. Just to be clear, there were no
you know, the FDIC didn't need to step in.
There was no deposit insurance implications.
Silvergate was able to pay everybody all the depositors back all their funds.
And then when we no longer had any deposits,
we wanted to return our bank charter so that we could no longer be a bank
since we weren't operating as a bank.
That process is a complex one that took a long time
through that process to find a path forward.
We we had to reach settlements with all the various regulators.
We did reach those settlements.
We then continued to unwind or, you know, unwind to the institution.
We filed for bankruptcy.
We're now sitting at a bankruptcy court in Delaware.
And, you know,
future decisions will be made or confirmed by the bankruptcy court.
So we'll come back to that later, but I want to look at the collapse.
So, you know, there's a lot of factors that you could look at and say,
OK, that was the factor.
Because if you look at a voluntary liquidation of a bank,
basically never happens. I looked into it.
There's not a lot of examples, certainly not of a good sized bank.
OK, so I think that in of itself, if I may editorialize here,
I think that's very suspicious, right?
Implies some sort of exogenous force there.
So there's almost never a voluntary liquidation.
So then the question is what drove that?
And you're telling me you had short dated
maturity assets backing the deposit.
So you were able to handle the outflows, you know,
unlike a bank that suffers a classic bank run where they can't meet liquidity,
but liquidity or solvency crisis.
That wasn't really the case here.
So, you know, with a lot of the other banks during this crisis,
they had longer dated assets.
Fed raises rates, valid those assets, declines.
You know, they have a kind of like a classic issue.
Then there's obviously, you know, what's been reported,
like in the day one bankruptcy filing, the CAO, Elaine Hetrick,
echoing what you've just said.
She said the increased supervisory pressure on Silvergate for Silvergate
to a point where it would have to need have needed to remake its business model
away from its focus on crypto asset businesses,
seek to selling itself as going concern in the shadow of regulatory overhang.
That was a more recent filing that came out.
There is the fact that Elizabeth Warren
had written some very nasty letters about to Silvergate leadership.
There was a short seller campaign.
So, I mean, is it just the totality of these factors
that were ultimately responsible for the wind down?
How do you sort of like rank them?
Um, no, I wouldn't say it was the totality of factor.
I think it's actually pretty simple.
And there were, you know, short sellers and there were
you mentioned Senator Warner and Warren
took activity that was either exploited by or or coordinated
with the short sellers, which was was harmful.
But really, the the issue for us was as simple as we had a business model.
It had been in place for.
10 plus years, you know, at that point, and our regulators
said that that business model is we can't allow that to continue.
That business model is not acceptable to us.
And so then we as a bank had to figure out a way to pivot away from that
to a new business model.
We couldn't identify one, just couldn't identify one that would
get a good result for our, you know, our shareholders and our employees.
So we had to just shut down.
We thought that was the right thing to do.
And you're right, by the way, voluntary liquidation is extremely rare
to the point where our primary regulator was in our charter was out of California.
I don't think they'd ever seen it before.
They didn't really know how to handle it.
And so that was something we all had to work through together.
So Elaine Hetrick's day one filing, you agree with her
characterization there that I just quoted.
Yes, I do.
So is it fair to say that it had not been for the regulatory shift?
Silvergate could have post bank run post FJX crisis,
resumed operations and been a functional bank today.
Yeah, I think more than functional.
I think it could have been a successful, compliant, well run,
much larger institution.
I mean, given the nature of crypto and the recent run up
we've had as an industry and the fact that the industry is maturing and growing,
I think Silvergate, it was it was a, you know, indispensable.
I thought part of that
ecosystem and it would be bigger than ever, in my view.
So a devil's advocate here, you know, a lot of critics tell me
I'd obviously written about debanking stuff, which I'm sure you're familiar with.
You know, they say, well, you know, crypto is a risky industry.
Should banks even be allowed to bank it?
Shouldn't it be ring fenced from the traditional financial system?
What's your view on that?
Like, how would you respond to that?
I'd say, yes, crypto is a risky industry by traditional banking standards.
And what that means is banks should be thoughtful about how they approach it
and regulators should be thoughtful about it.
It's a a legal industry that's changing the nature of finance
and will be changing the nature of other other industries in the future.
It's it's a critical industry, I think, for the future of American
the American economy.
I think it needs access to the banking system.
If it doesn't, by the way, it won't be in the United States.
It'll just go elsewhere.
And the risks we're talking about are risks that can be handled.
I mean, as I mentioned,
Silvergate survived a very large run of the bank by traditional standards
and did it just because it recognized we're in a volatile industry.
There are some special things about crypto.
Now, there's still a very successful business model to be maintained
while being careful and prudent.
So, yeah, to me, yes, there are risks that are unique to crypto
and there are ways to deal with them.
And it's not even that tough, to be honest with you.
So it's because, you know, I always hear from regulators, well, you know,
OK, maybe banks can serve crypto, but it should only be a
de minimis part of their business.
Crypto is too volatile.
Balance sheets expand and contract.
And we don't want banks dealing with that.
But you're telling me Silvergate had found the resolution of that,
which is hold short dated maturity assets or cash, cash equivalents.
So you can deal with those outflows when and if they occur.
Yes. And not only that, it was stress tested in real life and it survived.
Yeah. So, yeah, that's that's my opinion on it anyway.
I'm very comfortable that banks should be supporting that into the industry
and that if banks don't, I think there's collateral consequences
for the US economy and competitiveness and everything else.
So one thing I have to address, and when I started looking into Silvergate,
a lot of people told me, well, you know, actually, you shouldn't
be sympathetic to them because they banked Alameda or entities associated with them.
So, of course, we have to address this.
Silvergate did serve some of the entities that were in the Alameda
slash FTX apparatus.
What was the what's kind of Silvergate's version of that story?
Yeah, we did. We did bank Alameda first.
And then FTX and a couple of entities, a significant part of our,
you know, business there, their substantial customers for Silvergate.
The story is pretty simple. We've got a lawsuit against them.
We were victims and I'd argue double and in some ways, triple victims
of a fraud that was perpetrated.
I mean, we we asked questions,
received answers that made sense, that were just completely dishonest.
Yeah, I would also note that it's not just silver
getting claims that that we were defrauded by FTX,
but it's the Department of Justice has recognized.
And in fact, in the Sam Babin Free trial, we were identified as
as one of the larger victims of his actions.
Yeah. And I mean, this was one of the refrains I heard from the short sellers
or after FTX collapse was, you know, Silvergate aided and abetted.
I mean, it's just the opposite.
You guys were a victim and we absolutely were a victim.
And I mentioned a double or triple victim.
We were a victim to the to the FTX actions in the sense that they were a customer
and they, you know, we lost funds there.
The second way we're a victim was that there's a run in the bank
that was directly linked to that, you know, it affected the whole ecosystem.
But it was very much a run on Silvergate.
And then the third way we were a victim to this, I think, was the regulators actions.
I don't know what drove the regulators actions towards Silvergate,
but they followed shortly after FTX.
And I think it makes sense that there was a reaction to the FTX
the matter and the ultimate result was to close Silvergate
had to allow them to to move forward.
So financial loss, reputational loss, change in regulatory outlook.
I mean, it doesn't get worse than that.
Now, in terms of like, you know, basically no one saw the FTX fraud coming.
You know, we'd actually we received the FTX pitch back in the day.
We passed on it because we just didn't think Sam was very credible, believe it or not.
But with the benefit of hindsight, do you think the fraud could have been detectable
from looking at the flows between the entities that banked with you?
Yeah, sure. The benefit of hindsight, you can identify things.
Everybody, everybody could.
I'll tell you that there are a couple of things that banks do have obligations
and a lot of their customers absolutely no doubt about it.
But there's an awful lot that banks never know about
what their customers are doing.
And it's impossible to know about what, you know, all of your customers
are up to at all times.
I think that as technology gets better, we are as an industry,
the banking industry getting better and better at catching
fraudulent activity and other things.
I think given the state of the industry at that time,
it would have been probably not impossible,
but extremely difficult to identify those in advance. Yep.
And it is an interesting feature of the bank system.
The banks are expected to be cops, you know, they're deputized
and they're meant to be doing this non-bank activity,
which is being cops for their clients.
And it's just there's only so much you can figure out.
Now, I want to talk about signatures.
Well, you brought them up.
Barney Frank did speak out after they were sent into receivership
and sold off. He said they were basically killed
because their association with crypto.
As you said, their crypto deposits were not included
in the sale of NYCB.
The Cygnet product, which was also a very popular
settlement product that was not sold.
I mean, this is all pretty suspicious, right?
You know, they at the 11th hour, Barney Frank claims they're solvent.
They're sent into receivership.
We don't know what's going on there with NYDFS.
Then the crypto part of the business is stripped out
and not included in the sale.
This review is equally as suspicious I do, presumably.
Absolutely.
I mean, I think it's very clear that the regulator
is sending a message to the broader financial
system telling banks that this is not
this is not something we want you involved in.
I don't think signature is even given the opportunity
to try to raise funds there.
I think they were taken over very quickly.
And the crypto assets, it's strange to me at the FDIC
who's got a mandate to maximize, you know, their return,
chose not to sell assets that had real value.
But that's sending a message.
So I want to look at San as well here.
Silvergate Exchange Network.
So at the time there was seven signate seven signate, you know,
the value of those networks was because you had a ton of clients
that were all on boarded with you and they wanted to settle with each other.
Market making firms, trading firms, exchanges, stable coins
settle at all times. Very useful.
It's one of the things I regret still, frankly,
about this whole situation is the loss of sun.
Now, in the case in the ultimate settlement with California
financial regulator and I think echoed by the Fed,
you know, the the CAFP found that Silvergate had quote deficiencies
with respect to Silvergate's monitoring of internal transactions.
Can you sort of elucidate what happened there?
Yeah, in the first place, let me let me get back to those settlements.
What there are there is allegations and just to be to be clear
as part of that settlement, Silvergate
neither admits nor denies the accuracy of those allegations.
The but the upshot is is
there was the allegations were that not all internal transfers
were sufficiently monitored, electronically monitored in real time.
The Silvergate response to that was was several fold,
one of which is that there's no legal obligation to monitor internal transfers
that and they were being monitored
to the best of our technology at that time.
They were being monitored manually and
with investigative work until we were able to get systems up in place
that were monitoring them real time.
And that, in fact, I believe Silvergate was the only maybe signature was,
but sorry, it was the only bank in the country
that was actually monitoring internal transfers in real time.
And that, you know, so that's that's what it was.
But because of the SEND network,
we had a large number of transfers that were staying again within the bank,
but we're rotating around between customers in the bank.
And to be really clear,
I think everyone agrees that that's meaning that agencies and everyone else
that when any payments left Silvergate and went outside to another institution
or another customer, they were properly monitored at all times.
So the issue was was was limited to allegations about the internal transfers.
Yeah, I mean, I think that's something that many people did not understand
about the sign is that every transaction was happening
between a client that's already known to Silvergate
and had already been through the entire, you know, KYC and onboarding process
at Silvergate, which was it at that time and to this day,
I think was was recognized as among, if not the most stringent in the in the industry.
So I also want to acknowledge the settlements with the Fed,
the SEC and the CA DFP.
I know you're limited in what you can say about them,
but it's sort of the long and short of what the resolution was there.
Yeah, I mean, the resolution was, again, as a board,
we made a decision to shut down the bank and at that point we had to move forward.
And so the the only way we could see to move forward
in any kind of reasonable time frame involved reaching a settlement.
And we thought that was the the prudent thing to do,
the financially responsible thing to do.
And the right thing to do is who do you share is for our shareholders and everyone else.
And now it's a it's a shame, by the way, because what gets lost in all this
in the shutdown is, you know, 500 employees lost their jobs and 17.
I don't know how many jobs were lost by the 1700 clients of Silvergate,
but there were a lot of jobs lost, a lot of people harmed.
And in my view, it was unnecessary.
I sit on the other side of the table, right?
I represent the startups that are trying to be banked.
And this is why I got so interested in the issue is because our startups were debanked.
So from my perspective, capital formation startup growth was significantly impaired
by the loss of Silvergate and the general loss of banking.
Yeah, I agree with that.
Were you surprised at all that Silvergate's primary
primary regulators plus the SEC, the securities regulator,
came for Silvergate after the liquidation?
The announcement of the liquidation of the bank?
Yeah, it was the whole thing was surprising to me.
I will say that I felt very naive about the way I had lived my life
up until until a couple of years ago when the regulators came after us,
because it felt the entire process felt very political and very divorced from reality.
And, you know, unfortunately, there's a lot of examples
I wish I could go into were not permitted to.
But it just felt like the whole thing was political and that they were not.
In my view, they were not serving the American people well,
or the people of California well in the way it was approached.
So speaking of not serving the American people well, I want to talk about Diem.
No one ever talks about Diem here.
So I briefly had a footnote about Diem in my last article
because it's just this whole other story.
And then after, you know, after Coinbase started making progress
in their foyers against the FDIC, then I had David Marcus talking about Diem saying,
you know, they were rug pulled.
And that was such a long saga.
But Silvergate's involvement was, I believe, Silvergate was meant to be involved
in the Libra Consortium.
And then Silvergate ultimately bought the Diem assets.
And then that IP was just basically shuttered.
It became worthless.
Will you tell me from your perspective what happened with Diem?
Yeah, I enjoy reading David Marcus's stuff.
And David's exactly accurate from my standpoint and how it was handled
up to the point he ended his involvement.
Where Silvergate came in is, I will say, it goes back to,
maybe you can view this as another rug pull,
but it goes back to January 2021 that the President Biden had a working group
that looked at stablecoins and stablecoin issuance.
And among the things they did is this presidential working group
on financial markets, it was called.
They said stablecoins should be issued by an insured depository institution.
And Silvergate, at that point, we've been in this space for a long time.
We felt like we were sophisticated in this space.
We felt we were uniquely positioned as perhaps the only insured depository institution
that really understood the space.
And so we're familiar with Libra and Diem.
And so ultimately, Silvergate purchased the Diem assets,
intending to move forward and to start issuing a stablecoin through that technology.
Unfortunately, what we found is that the regulators,
again, changed their posture on that.
We were never able to get it approved.
And it ultimately became an asset of the bankrupt estate,
which is what it is right now.
So Silvergate got the impression from the Biden administration at the time
that Silvergate would be a suitable home for the Diem assets.
Yes.
And then that was just radically altered.
I mean, especially in 2023 when the Fed said they didn't want banks to touch stablecoins.
I think that's exactly right.
Now, by the way, I'll mention the Fed has now swapped positions pretty dramatically.
It's been interesting to me that the Federal Reserve Bank was
a major regulator of Silvergate Bank.
We went through this adventure with the Federal Reserve.
And then I see Chairman Powell of the Fed making statements.
And I think his most recent statement said, we're not against innovation.
And we don't want to take any actions that would lead to debanking.
In my view, that's a very significant pivot from where they were in their dealings with us.
Yeah.
I mean, even from the public statements, you know, in Jan 23, the Fed, the FDIC and the OCC
had the joint statement.
They said crypto is the rest of the safety and soundness of banks.
Then I think in August of 23, the Fed comes out and says,
look, banks can do stablecoins if you need a permission slip from us.
Basically implies you can't do stablecoins.
You had side 121.
If you're a bank, you can't really hold crypto assets on behalf of customers.
Basically, I mean, the whole posture was maximum hostile.
And it's remarkable that Jay Powell is changing his tune.
I mean, just a few weeks.
You know, let's administration.
I'm going to say I'm going to say it's thankful that he is, you know,
and I'm not going to appreciate the fact that he's willing to move forward.
Hopefully, and he said nice words and they've said words before.
But I think this time there's more to it.
I think this time there will be some change coming.
I think the Fed will be more responsive, more receptive to innovation in the space.
So, you know, speaking of changes in Washington,
obviously we have hearings in the House and the Senate around debanking
on specifically referencing Operation Choke Point 2.0,
which is what we encrypt to call the whole saga.
It's not the story doesn't just send there, you know,
the new interim chair at the FDIC is said he's going to look into it.
Trump himself said he would end Operation Choke Point.
David Sacks said he would end it.
You know, so it's a market tonal shift in Washington.
I think we will get information.
How optimistic are you that the hearings or maybe congressional investigations
will surface more information about what happened here in terms of regulatory shift?
I'm very optimistic they'll surface more information about it.
And I think there will be some changes, which I think is great.
I think, unfortunately, all the changes that we're going to see deal with, you know,
we're fighting fights that we never needed to fight in the first place from my perspective.
There are some real issues that the crypto industry needs to
figure out the right, you know, the right way to address.
I mean, there's, from my perspective, BSA, AML issues are significant.
We need to figure that out exactly how we're going to make that work.
You know, sanctions, we got to make sure that we're on top of it.
There's a lot of real issues.
This debanking one is is a political issue that was created and didn't need to happen.
In the hearings, if you look at the witnesses, there aren't a lot of bankers, actually.
So there's, you know, Nathan McCauley and Anchorage, they have a charter.
I'm not.
There's one banker from Old Glory Bank, which I don't know much about, actually.
But you're not hearing from Signature.
You're not hearing from Silvergate.
Why is that?
Are there prohibitions on executives of these organizations sharing their story?
It's fair to say that there's no prohibition against them appearing before Congress,
but there's absolutely restrictions on what we can say and can't say.
And I've talked to you just during this conversation we've had,
there's been a couple of times I would like to talk about that.
You have to stay away from what's known as confidential supervisory information.
And it's actually a violation of criminal law to disclose
confidential supervisory information that you receive from your regulators.
That is normally intended to be a shield for banks
so that they can receive candid information to regulators, not have to share it with the world.
But in this case, I think it's being used the other way.
I think it's being used to shield the regulators because anybody who has testified
would have to be concerned about the possibility that they'd violate the law inadvertently.
So that's a big part of it.
I'd say another big part of it is, you know,
many people are still facing lawsuits and other things that they don't want to
create exposure for, or they're continuing in the industry.
And if you're continuing in the industry, you for sure don't want to tick off your regulators.
So I suspect that's what's going on.
And that's the thing that struck me about this is there's such a lack of a paper trail.
There's so few people that are willing to go on the record.
I mean, I'm incredibly grateful that you chose to speak with me today.
I know it takes a lot of bravery to do that, given everything you've been through.
And frankly, the continued threat of settlements, enforcements, et cetera.
I mean, the CSI doctrine makes it hard to speak.
The threat of lawsuits, regulatory harassment makes it hard to speak.
And I'm just hopeful that maybe congressional investigations
will reveal the thought process at the regulators.
But I guess that's to be determined still.
Yeah, I hope that comes out.
One of the things that I'd like to make sure people understand is that
you're extremely unlikely to see a smoking gun memo sent from a regulator to a bank.
That's just not the way bank regulation works.
Bank regulators have such plenary authority over the banks they're regulating that
they merely ask a question.
It's enough to cause most banks to debank someone, right?
If they're just a side-eye glance is almost all it takes.
And it's a shame because this stuff should be done in a more transparent way.
But from the banker's standpoint, you're not going to risk your whole institution
for one customer.
And if the customer is causing any concern at all for your regulator,
the odds are high you're going to drop that customer.
So I have a wish list of changes I would like to bank regulation.
Not that I am an authority on it at all.
But I have been spending a lot of time on it over the last two years,
almost to the day, actually, is when I first published my first article.
And I have things that I want.
But if you were in charge of reforming bank regulation,
what changes would you make to the way it works?
Yeah, you know, it's interesting.
I think the biggest, my biggest takeaway from all this
was simply we were getting away from the way it's supposed to work.
That was the biggest problem we had is that we were not,
from my perspective, the regulators were getting involved in political issues.
Or there are political calls being made in Washington, D.C.
They're being communicated down to the regulators.
So they were actually not, from my perspective,
using their best regulatory judgment and acting in a good faith way
to fulfill their mission.
They were instead being directed to do certain things.
So I don't think the issue is primarily a legislative one.
I think the issue was more congressional oversight,
which I'm glad they're doing it.
A change in administration, which I'm glad there's been some accountability.
And I think, by the way, the crypto industry actually did
instill some accountability by getting involved in elections,
both in the presidential and Senate and other areas.
But I don't have any specific legislative changes I would make.
You made a reference to the fact that a lot of the enforcement work,
the police enforcement work of the government
has been offloaded to financial institutions.
That is absolutely true, but I don't think that's likely to change.
And that's where a lot of this issue is.
That would be a legislative change,
but I don't think it's one that can get through.
Yeah, as long as the Bank Secrecy Act is in place, that's not going to change.
Now, in terms of the Trump administration's ability to tackle this,
it's been a stated priority.
I'm very excited to see both houses looking into it.
Your level of optimism around basically getting to bottom this
or resolving it is fairly high.
Is that fair to say?
Yes.
Yeah, I think the administration is taking aggressive good steps in this area.
I think Congress is looking into it.
It's very difficult to get to the bottom of regulatory matters.
People are pretty good at covering their behind, and they probably did so there.
One thing I'll mention is, as you're looking forward,
we're talking about regulatory actions in the future.
I am confident the federal government is going to focus on what real issues in this space.
I know people in the industry should know that they can't get away with acting like
there's no regulations.
There's going to be a lot of regulatory enforcement.
You got to be careful about everything you do.
And I mentioned BSA, terrorist financing, sanctions,
all kinds of stuff that we need to be very careful about.
But I think the big change coming in the future is not going to come from the federal government.
I think states are going to be stepping up in this space,
and I think the industry needs to be aware of that.
Because for better or worse, right now, crypto has become a political player
and identified as a political player.
And I think what that means is that there will be states where attorneys general and
governors and others, regulators, will seek to make political points
by going after the crypto industry.
And they do have the authority.
There's a lot of consumer protection.
There's a lot of state blue sky security laws.
There's other ways states will be involved.
So I don't think that the change in government in D.C.
is some kind of panacea for the industry where it's all going to be roses.
But I do think it's better.
It's absolutely going to be better.
It's making a huge, it's going to be a big change.
And I think it's going to enable U.S. companies
to get back to doing what they should be doing,
which is building good companies, providing good services.
So I think it's taken a couple of worries off the table
and maybe it's added one or two others.
To my understanding, this is one of the first times you've spoken on the record
since the dissolution of Silvergate.
If you wanted to set the record straight on something that we haven't covered today,
what's kind of a misconception about the bank that you want to resolve?
It frustrates me that people think that somehow
Silvergate was in some ways in cahoots with FTX or anybody else
and was a bad actor in this.
I am 100,000% convinced that Silvergate was not a malicious or bad actor.
And that's a message it's got to get out.
I'm also extremely frustrated by the fact that short sellers,
sometimes working with Congressional and Senate officeholders,
are able to just say outrageously false statements with complete impunity.
And we need to figure out a way.
If you ask for a regular or legal change,
I would love to see short sellers face some liability
for making malicious and false statements in kind of a reverse pump and dump
because they're trying to make money by driving the stock of prices down.
That I would love to see.
But that'd be the biggest thing.
Other than that, I think people should know that from my perspective,
Silvergate was a bank that tried to do it right and I think did do it right.
Not perfectly, but did do it right and was, in my view,
killed unnecessarily by regulators.
And there's a different world where that didn't need to happen.
And it makes me sad that, you know, that institution is gone.
And as I mentioned, the employees are gone.
The investors lost their money or a big chunk of their money.
And all the customers are out scrambling, still looking for banks, many of them.
Yeah. And, you know, I actually forgot to ask this,
but like in terms of the future for common or even preferred shareholders,
is there a case against the government?
Is there a regulatory takings case?
I've heard this idea batted around.
Is there any kind of prospect of recovery beyond the assets that exist in the bank?
All that's in the bankruptcy court right now.
There isn't any lawsuits as an asset of the bankruptcy, you know, the estate.
And it will not be my decision how to pursue that.
A U.S. trustee or a bankruptcy court will be approving any action like that.
So I don't know whether it's going to go forward,
but to the extent there's a claim, it belongs to the estate.
In terms of your next steps, I mean, we haven't talked about that at all.
You know, what's your plan?
I'm excited about this industry.
I'm excited about, you know, the sort of little niche role I've managed to carve out in it,
which is to help help companies deal with regulation and help financial,
you know, help banks deal with it.
I'm I don't know what my next step.
I'm active now.
I'm on, you know, fully busy.
My plate is full right now.
I don't see any critical change coming.
But I'm excited by what the next few years are going to bring.
And I think some of the companies that I'm working with
are going to be quite large and quite successful.
And it's a ton of fun.
I also think, by the way, that somebody else is going to recreate Silvergate Bank.
It's going to happen.
And it's a shame it's not going to be Silvergate,
but that somebody else is going to be offering those same services to this industry.
And it's going to be very successful at it.
And, you know, assuming that they're careful and I'm sure they will be
and that the regulators are prudent,
we'll end up with a safe, secure financial institution
that's offering all these services.
And I'm hopeful that Silvergate 1700 customers
and all the other customers out there are able to get get bank accounts,
get back into the economic system of the United States.
Well, I mean, despite the ordeal that you and your colleagues went through,
like I'm very heartened to see that you are still optimistic about the industry.
I don't know if I would be, but it's really great to see.
It wasn't the industry.
I don't feel like that, you know, that anything that went wrong at Silvergate
was not the crypto industry.
I mean, you know, obviously, FTX would have been better if that hadn't happened.
But, you know, the strengths of the industry so far outweigh any weaknesses.
And I think the issue that Silvergate had was honestly a change in policy
with the regulators that, you know, my view was done in the dark,
in a back room somewhere without proper public discussion.
And, you know, that's now been corrected.
The new president was elected in part on that.
And so I'm very optimistic, actually, where this is going.
Well, Mike, I can't express my gratitude enough.
Thank you so much for coming on and sharing your story with us.
And it's been such a pleasure to have you on.
Great. Thank you.
I thank you. I should have said early for the report you've done in space.
It's been, I think, spot on from my perspective and very helpful.
Well, here's to things getting better.